{
  "reference_number": "9495",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It's important to be accountable now!! and also give individuals, groups and businesses the information what and how they can work\n towards; cimate change is real, the govt has acknowledged this with changing its military strategy, insurances and growers and\n farmers know it's here, coastal communities, too. Just legislators and large corporates need to catch up asap."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "All gasses are affecting climate change. Methane produced by ruminants must be included as they are such a huge contributor of\n\n our total greenhouse emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Also there should be support of, and perhaps reward for green technology and innovation. Change to electric public transport\n vehicles, rail and support for vehicle sharing, cycling and improved pubic transport. If we rely on others we don't really have the price\n\n or the quantities in our hands. We need to build the capacity to do it all here. New forest planting can only be taken into account if it is\n done for primary forest not for commercial forestry as the latter provides only temporary carbon capture and will result in additional\n emmissions further down the line. Reduction has to be achieved to a behavioural shift, real car sharing not Uber-cheating taxi service."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only in reducing it sooner if innovations prove effective or if climate change progresses more rapidly or in general any\n\n changes need to occur in favour of the environment, even if it hurts a bit. Because the big pain will come if we are not prepared to\n take the little pain."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes in giving time frames and milestones, clearer goals can be targeted and reached. Each time frame also allows for resetting of\n budgets to ensure the 15 year goal is reached."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "as the effects of climte change are never as intimately relateable to a disaster, a conservative govt would simply change to their\n political liking and on re-election rather than a true environmental goal/budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes there needs to be some flexibility due to unpredictable changes in science, technology, natural disasters, less in economy as we\nhave to pull through this in order to come out the other end and the reason why we are where we are in this predicament is that $$-\n\neconomy has always won over eco-economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Livestock Farmers - to assist with reducing methane emissions, erosion, transition to sustainable organic polyculture land fertility\n\npractices, planting of waterways and wetlands and fencing vulnerable areas. Horticulture -assistance with moving away from huge\nmonoculture and chemical practices which destroys biodiversity and in fact erodes the livelyhood of farmers. Transport - transition to\ntrain, monorail, public transport EVs and cycling. Industry and Importers: Single use items taxed or discouraged in other forms,\n\nContainer Deposit Legislation schemes (also for tyres, batteries, beverages, even takeaway meal containers, in general all plastic\ncontainers) , Stewardship schemes, cradle-grave schemes and need to be supported by the single use items tax."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, for a democratic process it is essential that the Government is accountable to an Independent private commission which\n\nrepresents us and is the capable, knowledgeable \"checks and balance\" function."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I still think we should have a carbon tax instead!!! it feels wrong to trade the health of the earth and humanity in a capitalistic system,\nthat's what got us here in the first place."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, they should be highly regarded people with a variety of expertise such as in climate change and environmental science,\n\nbusiness, engineering, social policy, Maori interests, and communication. There needs to be a gender balance of 50:50 and include\nwahine Maori of course."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There are unknowns in the predictions around climate change so there needs to be flexibility around dealing with these. Every day\n\nwe encounter new information how CC is impacting in a way we have never thought about it. But it needs to change only pro\nenvironment not economy-related etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "with the impacts of climate change happening more frequently we need better plans and policies in dealing with these issues.\nTherefore we need more understanding of the science of these effects eg on our biodiversity, and human health to better deal with\n\nthem."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This issue affects everyone and in particular the already disadvantaged in communities more. It is therefore wise to share information\nand support"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am involved in a very progressive local community gardenand an active Transition Towns Pt Chevalier member where we discuss CC\nissues and trying to do our informed bit as much as we can - we could have a bigger impact if govt sets targets and we are enabled\n\nto recruit more people on board to help reach these targets on an individual/household local basis. I am actively involved in activities\nwith the group to support sustainable living practices. I also feel we as a quite wealthy country must address some of the excessive\n\ndamage we have created to climate change that is affecting our Pacific Island neighbours who are suffering the most and have been\nminimal emitters. It is because of these interests and social concerns and my concern for the planet and for future generations that I\n\nfully support the Green Party in its aim to pass the Zero Carbon Act as proposed. My partner and I don't have children and are in our\nmid-late 50s, we could just go ahead, enjoy our live and fcku up the planet as there's no blood-relative coming after us - but that's not\nhow we think, we want as many people as fit healthily on this earth without living over its boundaries to enjoy the one life they are\n\ngiven - just as we are allowed to.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
